This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine online at
computer.org/software.
[music]
Welcome to Software Engineering Radio.
I'm your host Giovanni Asproni and today
I will be discussing even sourcing with
Martin Dilger. Martin is the founder and
CEO of Nebuildt GmbH and he is a
consultancy on helping software teams
design and implement even driven systems
using even modeling and even sourcing.
He's also the author of the book
Understanding Even Sourcing and a
frequent conference speaker. Finally,
he's a co-host with Adam Dmytruk of the
even modeling and even sourcing podcast.
Martin, welcome to Software Engineering
Radio. Is there anything I missed you'd
like to add? Hello Giovanni. Very glad
to be here. Thanks for the invitation.
No, that was a very kind introduction.
Thank you. Okay. So, I want to mention
an episode related to this one that is
episode 539 with Adam Dmytruk that was
on even modeling. So, in this one we'll
actually specifically focus on even
sourcing. We'll mention of course the
relationship between the two because is
important, yeah? But it'll be mostly
about even sourcing, yeah? Yes. Great.
So, for the listeners that want to know
more about even modeling we have the
other episode they can look into. And
now, let's start with a simple question
for you, Martin. That is, what is even
sourcing in a few words? You really
think that is a simple question? Many
teams struggle with this.
[laughter]
So, in essence many people start to look
at it from a technical perspective. So,
if you want to look at it from a
technical perspective because we also
have a technical audience, it's just a
different way to store information and
to process information. So, if you look
at a typical CRUD architecture, what
we're doing is we're just storing
structured objects without any history.
And even sourcing turns this around a
little bit and we just we store a whole
history of things that happen in our
system in the form of events. That's the
only thing that event sourcing brings
in. And this has some quite interesting
effects on information processing and
how you structure your whole system.
Okay. Can you give me quickly just a
small example maybe of system you worked
on about this or just to give the
audience an idea of what may look like
system like this I mean. Yeah, of
course. So, for example, I'm currently
working on a system that processes law
information. So, it's in the law space.
So, working a lot together with law
agents. And what we do there is if you
open a new case, instead of storing the
typical case information in a table that
is called cases, we just store a new
event which is called case created for
example. And whenever there is a new
case in the system, there is a new event
that is stored case created. And then
you have a complete history of all those
cases. And you can just look it up when
was this case created, who created this
case, all the information is stored.
Thank you. And the terminology,
terminology around events in software
can be really, really confusing. So,
what are the relationships, if any,
between event sourcing, event streaming,
event storming, event driven? There is a
lot of
event modeling. That of course is also a
term.
course, yeah. Yes, you're right. Yeah,
the problem is actually I don't like the
term at all because it's so bloated.
Whenever you say event, you can ask two
developers and you will get three
answers at least. So, many people have a
very different understanding. And also,
as you mentioned, there is event
streaming, there is event storming, all
those different terminologies all around
events and they mean very, very
different things. So, first of all, when
I say event, what I mean with this is
not a technical term. An event is just
something that happened in the system.
It's a fact that happened in the system.
It's not a technical term at all. I'm
really looking at information systems
and I typically refer to software
systems as information systems. I really
look at them from a business
perspective. So, an event is just
something that happened in the system
from a business perspective. Any
business person can understand this
immediately. Something that happened in
the system, that's all. All that an
event is.
And now a bit of with event modeling
because event sourcing and modeling as
we said they are kind of strongly
related. So, event modeling in a few
words, what is that? Event modeling is
the starting point of any information
system. So, many of the listeners most
probably are familiar with event
storming which is very similar to event
modeling. Event modeling has just some
specialties that are different to event
storming, but in essence it's a
collaborative modeling technique. And
the idea of event storming and also
event modeling is you bring people
together very early in the process, very
early in the project also, and they
start to discuss things. You start to
discuss those problems because one thing
I realized a few years ago and that
changed my whole career was that the
problems we are facing in most of our
systems, in most projects, and I've been
in the industry for over 20 years, and
all those projects I was involved with,
they faced the same problems. It was
always communication. It was never
technology. It was always communication.
When you bring people together very
early in the project and you make them
talk to each other and really talk about
the problems, many of those problems
they simply seem to fade away. Because
when you make people talk to each other
and they really find this common
terminology, this common language,
everything seems to work suddenly. And
this is almost magical. And event
modeling, event storming, and all those
collaborative modeling techniques, they
do just that. Basically they enforce
good communication in the project,
especially together with event sourcing,
that's just a great combination to build
information systems. Okay, and so what
is the relationship with event sourcing?
We can follow what you said, event
modeling seems to be some level of I
don't know, in between requirements and
design maybe, high-level design, not
technical design of the system. Exactly.
So, what you do basically with event
modeling is you just describe an
information system from beginning to
end. The big difference to event
storming is in event modeling you do it
along one single timeline. So, it's like
you're telling a story. You're finding
the story of a system together with
engineering, together with the business
experts, and it's always readable from
left to right. And that's the amazing
thing because everybody knows how to
read from left to right. So, in an event
model you can start on the left side and
if you want to know how a certain
business process works, you can just go
from left to right step by step because
everything in the event model is laid
down step by step and you can understand
what happens in the system step by step.
Basically, it's like a prototype. You
can go through it like a prototype and
you see exactly screen by screen what is
going on in the system. And if you look
at that, it's a perfect blueprint to an
event-driven system and also to an event
source system. So, especially when you
work with modeling there is a very easy
mapping between your event model and the
event source system. It's so simple that
you can even use it to generate code.
This is what I'm doing a lot. I'm
generating a lot of code. So, I'm
sitting together with clients. We model
their processes, try to understand their
problems. And when we did that, we use
the event model directly to generate
code from this. And this really, really
interesting, really interesting way to
work. One thing that you wrote in your
book, you said that one of the most
interesting things about event sourcing
is that it's natural alignment with
human thinking. What do you mean with
that? When you develop systems without
event sourcing, so what happens when you
get a problem as a typical developer?
You sit down and the first thing a
developer thinks of is, "Okay, what is
the tables that I need?" Oh, let's take
a simple example. I need to build a user
registration. Almost every developer
will immediately think of a user and of
a users table and an address table and
the typical structural things you see in
the system. What they don't do is they
don't talk about the processes behind
that. But then you go to business, they
never think about tables. They never
think about users and those structured
classes you have in your system. They
think in processes. And when you use
event modeling and also event sourcing,
you start to think in processes because
when you think in events, it's always,
"Oh, this happened and then this
happened and then the user was
registered and then this notification
was sent." Very natural. Basically, you
can tell the story in natural language
and this can directly be mapped to an
event source system because that's
exactly what happens there. Going to
event sourcing more data now. So, of
course there are several parts we can
now discuss them all. When we talk about
internal external events, event stores,
projections, and other things. Oh yeah,
all those technicalities, yes. We really
have to talk about those. But, I'd like
to start with the core patterns because
again, reading your book followed by
Adam Dmytruk, he wrote, "Event sourcing
is not only revolutionary, but also
responsible." With just two core
patterns, it was remarkably simple. So,
what are these two core patterns?
Actually, I refer to them as four
patterns. Adam uses constant two
patterns, but I use four patterns
because for me that is simpler to
explain. So, in essence, that's what you
do when you use event modeling. You
break the system down into tiny little
steps. We call them slices. So,
basically what you have in the end is a
slice-based architecture, but you break
them down into slices. And there are
basically just two types of slices. The
first slice type is state change slice.
State change just means how does
information get into the system? There
are just two ways to get information
into the system. Typically, it's a
screen. You have a screen, a user clicks
on a button on the screen, fires a
command into the system, and if
everything goes well, there's a new
event in the system, a new information
that is stored in the system. That's a
state change slice. Basically, just
getting information into the system. And
the second slice type is a state fuse
slice. So, you use these events which
are already available in the system, and
you provide them for the next screen,
you provide them for the next background
process. That's all. Information getting
into the system, information getting out
of the system. And if you break the
system down into those patterns,
suddenly it becomes very simple because
every system in the world, no matter how
big it is, no matter how complicated it
is, can be broken down into state
changes and state fuses. And if you put
them together like LEGO bricks, that's
basically your system. And breaking
those systems down into those tiny
little steps makes it really easy to
reason about even the most complex
business processes because most
problems, if you break them down, they
become really simple. and it's really
amazing, and that's one of my biggest
learnings. Almost everything we do in
software development isn't complex. Most
of the things we do is rather simple if
you just break it down. They just look
so complicated if you look at those big
problems. And if you have the stories in
your estimations that last for 1,000
person days, well, that looks
intimidating, and that looks really
problematic. But if you break it down,
suddenly it's just 1,000 tiny steps in
this process. And every tiny step is
very simple in and of itself. Okay. And
now, let's go about the other parts. So,
again, maybe you can start telling us if
all the technicalities here. So, talking
about the events, the type of events,
the event store. So, tell us well, maybe
a story at this parts and connect them
together. How Yeah. the connecting them
together so we understand how it is even
sourcing is actually made here, is
composed of. Yeah. Maybe we can put in a
tiny little bit of event modeling here
before we dive into event sourcing
because it makes it easier to understand
where this leads. So, if you do an event
modeling workshop, it follows seven
steps. So, in the end, what we try to do
is we try to map out the system step by
step. And the first thing we do
typically is what's called the
brainstorming. There we we gather all
the people who are involved in the
project. So, in the first step,
brainstorming, many people can
participate in the workshop. Can be 30
people. I had event modeling workshops
with 30 people, and I do this a lot. I
do a lot of those workshops for
companies to help them get into event
modeling and also into event sourcing.
And the first part of the workshop is
always brainstorming. That means you
gather all the events. Just like putting
sticky notes on a giant whiteboard. And
this can be 100, this can be 500 events
depending on how many people
participate. But the interesting thing
is what we're already doing here is we
are shaping the ubiquitous language. And
every developer who's listening now will
immediately make the reference to
domain-driven design, and this is
exactly what we're doing there. It's
always difficult to find the ubiquitous
language. Ubiquitous language is
basically the one language we are having
in the project that everybody
understands. Engineers, business people,
security, everybody talks the same
language. When I say customer, everybody
knows what that means. In most projects,
that is absolutely not the case. We have
different terms for the same thing. You
say one thing and everybody understands
something different. One of the biggest
problems we have in our project. But
when you bring those people together and
you just make them put those terms,
those events on a board, suddenly those
people start to discuss, sometimes for
the first time in their life, what is
the right naming for this? Can we find a
common terminology for this? And this is
where we already start to shape the
ubiquitous language. The next thing that
we do is we try to bring them in an
order. This is where we form the story
of the whole system. I call it
storyboarding. It's just you take this
whole cloud of events and you try to
bring them in an order. This is where we
try to find the story of the system.
What happens one event after the other.
And just looking at the result of the
storyboarding is very interesting
because you can already see first, how
big is the system? And second, what
happens one step after the other. And
this already gives us an indication,
okay, what is the first thing that we
need to tackle? What is the second thing
that we need to tackle? The story is
really becomes visible only after that.
And this can be after 30 minutes. So,
storyboarding and the brainstorm, this
can be just 30 minutes and we already
start to to map out what happens in the
system. And the next thing that we do in
the event modeling is we draw screens.
Screens, also very, very important part
and this is a key differentiator to
event storming also. We heavily draw
screens. And screens is really important
because this allows everybody in the
project to understand what we are
discussing. So, if you leave out those
screens and I see this a lot in
workshops, people are confused because
business people, they are not used to
think in events and many, many engineers
are also not used to think in events.
Thinking in events, it's a different
thing. If you've been in the CRUD world
and you've developed CRUD based systems
for 20 years and you learned from
scratch building CRUD based systems,
thinking in events is all but natural to
you. And many people struggle with this.
But if you bring in screens to the
story, suddenly everything makes sense.
That's really you have something visual
and you can map the screen to the events
and that seems to work for everybody and
I see this very very often. Well, it's
really almost a visual prototype of what
the system may look like even if it is
not the final design or anything. It's
just about maybe the flows or the way it
works. Yes.
But it gives people an anchor in their
heads on how the system works, I guess,
and helps
Yes.
Okay. And many people try to skip this
because they think, "Oh, it's so time
intense to draw those screens. I don't
want to do this." I have a very simple
rule. If it takes you more than 2
minutes to draw a screen, you're
absolutely doing it wrong. 2 minutes is
the absolute maximum you must take to
draw a screen. So, in essence, if you do
event modeling, drawing ugly screens is
a key skill you need to master. My
screens are the worst. They're super
ugly and I'm really proud of that. So, I
can draw very good screens, very ugly,
but very efficient. The key thing why we
need those screens is you need to
understand what does the user see? Is
there a button? Is there an input field?
What is displayed? It doesn't matter if
it's a radio button or a checkbox or
something like that. UX people hate
this. They hate this in the beginning.
Because they want to discuss, of course,
the pixel-perfect screen designs, but
this is absolutely not what this is
about. So, it's really like, "Okay,
let's break this down step by step." And
what we see there already is we see the
slices slowly forming. Slices are the
building blocks in the system. What are
the screens? What are the events that we
have step by step? They're already you
can see how the event-driven and
event-sourced system slowly forms. And
the next thing that you do then is when
we have the screens and the events, we
just define what are the commands and
what are the read models. Now, we come a
little bit more into the terminology
that goes in the direction of event
sourcing. So, commands and read models
are basically just two important
elements. Like, what is a command? A
command is basically just an instruction
to the system. You want the system to do
something. So, register user, for
example, could be a command that you
send to the system and you want this
user to be registered. You don't know if
it works. You don't know what business
rules are behind it. You just send
command to the system. I want this user
to be registered. If everything goes
well, you have a new event in the
system. But of course, there's a lot of
validation going on because typically
every command that we send to the system
is backed by a whole lot of business
rules. But if everything goes well, a
successful command execution means there
is a new event in the system. But then,
if we progress in the story, so in the
event model we go from left to right,
there's a next screen that comes. And
this next screen shows a list of
registered users. Now you need to show
well, where does this list of users come
from? And there you just use the
information that is already available in
the system. It's the events, and you
project them to the screen. How do you
do a projection? That's a read model. In
event model, we call this a read model.
It's just a green sticky note that shows
you this is the information that is
displayed on the screen, and these are
the events that provide this
information. So what we are doing with
event modeling is we call this
information completeness. So for every
step in the system, you need to be very
sure where does this information come
from, so you cannot make any wrong
assumptions. What is the one of the
biggest problems you face in most
projects? It's wrong assumptions. You
just assume information to be available.
And then later, when you go into the
implementation, then you realize, and
that's very late in the project, then
you realize, oh, some of our
assumptions, they weren't right. That's
a problem because you already allocated
the budget, you already had the project
plan, you already planned your sprints,
you are ready to go into coding, but now
you realize well, we cannot do this. And
this is where it gets really, really
expensive because now you need to do the
re-planning. All the things you did
before was basically just a waste of
time. Event modeling turns this around.
We ask those questions in the very
beginning of the project, very early. So
if there is a gap in our requirements,
an email is not available, information
is not available, we know from the
beginning because you see it in the
event model. You cannot map the event
model if the information is not
available. So for every step basically,
we break it down and we know is the
information available or not. And to
build those screens, for example, you
need a read model, and back to the
terminology of event sourcing, that's
basically called a projection. You use
these events in the system and you
simply project them to the information
you need to display the screen. In your
book you say that using event sourcing
we are adding the dimension of time to
our system. So, the system records the
facts that happen along a timeline,
which you said with events at least,
things that happen. You said this
dimension gets lost when data is
flattened to a relational database
schema. Tell us more about that. Let's
go back to this example of the user
registration. So, what you have
typically in a traditional architecture
is just have a table with user
information, but you have to absolutely
no history how this information got in
there. Was this user registered? Was
this registered by an automatic process?
Was this done manually? Was this done by
an administrator? How often was this
user changed? All this information is
lost typically. If you need to know what
happened to this user, if you are lucky,
you can get into the logs or into your
temporal tables and find out what
happened to this user, but from an
architectural perspective, this
information gets flattened and it's
lost. And event sourcing is the exact
opposite of that. The timeline, the
information, how you got to a certain
point in the system, it's an essential
part of the architecture. So, you have
everything recorded, every decision you
made in the system, step by step, and
basically since the beginning of your
system. So, I have clients who work with
event sourcing for 10 and more years.
They have tons and tons of information
in their databases. Every decision ever
made in the last 10 years is recorded as
a fact, as an event in the system.
That's informational gold that they have
there. So, everything is recorded and
basically you throw this away
intentionally if you just store the
information and not the history behind
it. And I will never understand why you
would do this intentionally. For me this
makes no sense, not at all. I can say in
relational database you can store some
of that information surely. When
somebody registers a user you can put
this, you know, it's been automated or
somebody else, but if there are changes
during time on this information, that
that becomes a bit more difficult.
Sometimes there is some versioning of
stuff or versioning of tables, but that
becomes a bit more difficult in a
relational database to keep track of.
Oftentimes what you do is, of course,
companies need this information. So,
what they do is they need to work around
this. So, you work with temporal tables
which store information along a
timeline, but it's not really usable.
You cannot work with this information.
It's just there, but typically when I
ask a client, "How often did you use
your temporal tables?" The answer is
never because it doesn't work. Same
question, "How often did you use your
backup?" Well, never because it doesn't
work. Well, why are you doing then? It's
always the same thing. Yeah, it is
definitely more difficult to keep that
information in a reasonable manner. But,
also another thing then, well, a
question after this one because we say
we store every single decision and
forever, you know, 10 years and more.
But, then how do you manage this
information if it starts to become big?
If you start to have a lot of
information, a lot of data in your
databases. What do you do? Is there any
form of archiving of events, deletion of
old events? I don't know. Yeah, so of
course, I often discuss with clients who
want to learn about event sourcing, who
want to understand event sourcing, and
those are the first questions that
typically come. Wait a second, if you
store every decision, this will get
crazy because in a crud-based system we
simply overwrite the information and
then it's gone and so we have very clear
picture of how big this data is that we
store. In event sourcing it's basically
unlimited. How should we deal with that?
But, first of all, if you store events,
it doesn't get so big typically if you
do it right. So, it's not like you're
storing millions and millions of events
that you need to process to get to a
certain state. That's typically not what
happens. So, oftentimes what you do is
you store information per process. And a
process itself isn't infinitely large.
Your processes are typically very small
and contained. So, what you have is you
have streams of events and those streams
of events they are typically very small.
So if you want to know what happened to
this A question, when we say process we
mean what? A software process running or
a business process? I'm specifically
talking about the business process. So
you really look at the business
processes and typically you have the
history of your customer. A customer was
registered and a few more things that
happened to this customer. That's one
stream of events that you store in your
database or that you store in your event
store. But the history of this customer
isn't infinitely large. Maybe it's 10,
15, 20, 30 events or maybe it's 100
events. It doesn't really matter. All
those processes they're typically very
small and typically it doesn't happen
that you have to process millions of
events to get to a certain state. If you
do this typically there's a problem in
the modeling or in how you structure
your information. It shouldn't be the
case. And so, how many of these streams
are typical event source systems? So
that is a several streams. It depends on
the number of your business processes in
the system. So it doesn't really matter
how many streams you have. So typically
you just define those streams alongside
your business processes. So if there is
a customer registration that is a
dedicated stream. If there is a card
system that you have in your e-commerce
system that might be a dedicated stream.
A card session might be a dedicated
stream. So it's really you design your
processes. If you have events that
belong together to a business process
that typically also belongs to a stream.
And then there come a few other
terminologies. So typically then you
talk about aggregates or if you talk
about newer concepts in the event
sourcing that's DCB but we can talk
about this a little bit later. And also
in these streams, so if you have several
streams, can these streams be dependent
on each other? Are there any
dependencies that that you would need to
manage? It can is of course. So it can.
So typically what you try to do is you
try to contain those streams. So what
you try to do is you try to keep those
streams consistent. Within a stream you
only want to have consistent data. Same
as you try to have consistent data in
your traditional architectures. It's the
same idea. And if you build an event
source system, what you nowadays have
typically is you have an aggregate and
this aggregate is basically a protection
for your stream. So, if you send a
command to your system, the first thing
that happens typically is something in
your system just checks, can I execute
this command? Is this valid? If I
execute this command, will my system be
in a consistent state? And the thing
that does this typically is the
aggregate. It just sits basically on
your stream and checks, can I execute
this command or not? And typically, what
you try to do is you try to keep those
streams self-contained as much as
possible, but of course, there can be
dependencies between streams, but you
try to keep them as consistent as
possible in themselves. And when there
are dependencies, how do you manage
those? I'm thinking from the perspective
of if you want to rebuild the state of
the system at certain point in time. If
you have these dependencies, how do you
manage these different dependencies
across streams to have a consistent
state of your whole system? That's a
very good question and this is where
many teams really struggle because
oftentimes, so what teams come up with
when they reach that state is the the
saga pattern. The saga pattern is
basically how to define long-running
processes and keep the system consistent
even if it's across streams or even
across different systems. I never used
that in my systems. I don't need this.
What we do in event modeling basically
is we call this automations. It's
basically just another process step that
is responsible to use the information in
one stream and send it to another
stream. That's basically, you could call
it a tiny little saga, but typically, I
neither use the term saga pattern nor do
I use this concept in my systems. I
don't need it. But there's a small piece
of automation or a small piece of
software that just uses information from
one stream and knows how to transform
this information to another stream. And
that's how you manage those dependencies
typically. Okay. In terms of
performances because surely you'll have
this question all the time. Are there
any implications in terms of latency,
the time, memory, any performance
implications on these systems. So,
that's of course one of the biggest
question that comes up because many
people have a very wrong understanding
what event sourcing actually means. So,
if I talk to developers, what they think
is, well, if I want to know what my
customer looks like, every time I want
to know this, I go to my event store and
I read all the events of this customer
basically every time I need this
information. That is typically not what
happens. So, what you have in event
sourcing, and I use this a lot, is just
persisted projections. So, at runtime it
behaves exactly like every other
traditional architecture as well. So,
what happens basically whenever there is
a new event, this gets persisted to a
persisted projection, and this can be a
relational table, for example. So, at
runtime what you do is you read your
customer's table. It's still your
customer's table, but it's not your
source of truth, the customer's table,
but it's just a projection of the events
of this customer. And whenever you want
to change this, or you need new
information from this customer, you can
just build a new projection or two new
projections of this. You are very, very
flexible in how you work with your
information. Okay, so if I'm
understanding correctly, you have events
that you store somewhere, and then they
are facts, things that happened to a
data, but then every time an event
happens, we can update, say,
table in a relational database, which is
basically the most recent view of that
particular data set, as a customer, as
you said.
Exactly. Exactly. This can be like a
snapshot. Yes. And so, if I want to see
that at a past time, what I need to do
is rebuild that view, but up to a point.
So, not up to the most recent event, but
maybe an event, I don't know, 10 days
ago, because if I'm interested to data
in the past, I do that. Yes. For
example, if you want to do that, if you
need to And I do this a lot for bug
fixing, for example. That's exactly how
you do bug fixing in event sourcing. If
you want to know, what does the system
look at a certain point in time, you can
just build a new projection out of it,
use exactly the events to reproduce this
bug, and you know exactly what was the
state when the customer clicked this
button. And then you can just look,
okay, the user clicked this button, the
system was in that state. Well, that's
clear, this is the problem. Very
interesting way to work. And why is this
so powerful? If you define everything in
a table in the traditional architecture,
you have just your customer's table, and
all your use cases, they are using this
customer's table. That creates a ton of
coupling, and coupling is one of the
biggest problems we face in our
architectures, because now if you change
one of those use cases, you have to
retest all the other use cases, because
they all depend on the same tables, they
all depend on the same information. In
event sourcing, this completely goes
away, because what we're doing is we
define one projection for each of those
use cases. Every use case has its own
customer's table with just the
information that it needs. It doesn't
need everything in this table.
Typically, it's just a tiny fraction of
this information. So, you have not one
customer table, you have many small
customer tables, specific for those use
cases. And this gets rid of all those
coupling problems, and it's an amazing
way to define systems. And in terms of
evolution of events, because I can
imagine that over time, we want to
change some information, maybe as
example associated to a customer, maybe
you want to change the format of the
address, or add some more information.
Basically, you have a situation where
the events change in terms of what the
information they carry. So, how do you
manage this evolution? Yes, there are
different ways how to deal with it. So,
I always approach this in the same
order. So, the first thing I typically
check is if I need to change an event,
because maybe there is a new field. Is
this really just the structure change to
the event, or is this maybe a new event?
So, for example, if we need to add a
field to the customer address, maybe
this is like a postal code added event.
Can I just add a new event to the system
that basically brings this information
to the existing event? So, I try to not
change events if I don't have to. So,
that's always the first thing I try.
It's much easier to introduce new
events, as long as they have real
business meaning. So, I don't introduce
new events just for to introduce new
events, they need to be relevant to the
business but if that is the case, that's
my first choice always. But sometimes
this is not the case so very very stupid
example, there is a typo in in a field
in an event. Do you want to keep that or
do you want to change that? So sometimes
you just you need to make structural
changes to an event. And if that is the
case, what you typically do is you just
introduce a new version of this event so
events are typically versioned so that
would be then just a a customer
registered V2, a second version of this
event and then you can slowly and
gradually adjust all the projections
that depend on this event and then at
some point in time you just work with
this version two of the events. And if
you need to process those older versions
of an event, typically what you have is
the concept is called an upcaster and
that you basically take this first
version of the event and there is a
small piece of infrastructure that knows
how to transform this version one into a
version two so your system only from
this this point on has to work with the
version two of the event. That's
typically how you deal with those
things. Is there a risk that over time
you will write a lot of software in your
in your system to lots of upcasters if
you like? Yeah, I mean of course that
that can happen but in reality that is
typically not the case so your business
process they don't change over time and
typically business process they are very
stable and since what we are modeling
and what we are discussing is the
business process, they tend to be really
really stable. It's very different if
you look at it from a technical
perspective because the technicalities
in the project they change very quickly
but the processes themselves they are
typically very stable so yes in in
theory that could happen in practice
that is not what I see. Okay so in
practice is less of a problem that what
what it looks like. Yes. Basically.
Yeah, I can understand this because if
you established a ubiquitous language at
the beginning basically you are if I
understand correctly you are focusing a
lot on the business so the business
processes actually drive the shape of
the data and the information. Since
those processes change slowly, chances
for this data to change are actually not
that big at the end of the day.
Instead, if we go the other way around,
if we model the information without
considering the business processes from
the beginning, we may end up in a
situation where we keep changing those
much more frequently. Am I understanding
correctly? Yes, absolutely. That's
exactly the point. And what is also the
point is those events, they are really
happening at very specific points in the
process. So, typically, if you refactor
an existing database, often this has
effects all over the place in the system
typically. But, if you just change this
one event, the effect is very, very
small and very contained. So, even if
you change one event, it typically
doesn't affect all the other places in
the system. So, changes in the system
are very contained in in very small
area. So, it's typically not a big
problem. Okay. And let's talk a bit
about adoption. Yeah? So, the first
question I have about this is, what kind
of difficult topic?
[laughter]
Why you think is difficult? Is adoption
something that is complicated for teams
in general or Yes. So, first of all,
event sourcing, I don't know why, but
most companies are terrified to death
from event sourcing. They're really
afraid of applying it, of doing it. And
I I I don't really know why that is. So,
I could never find out why this is the
case, but whenever I I mention event
sourcing to a company, they immediately
go, "Oh, no, no, no, no. We tried that
once. We miserably failed and then we
will never ever do it again." Well,
that's not really a problem of event
sourcing. That's just either you applied
it wrong or maybe there was a problem in
the modeling. So, typically, it's not
Whenever we have this discussion and we
dig a little bit deeper, it's not a
problem of event sourcing. It's
typically a problem, "Oh, you applied it
wrong." Let me give you a very, very
prominent example, something I see very,
very often. Customers tell me, "Well, we
tried event sourcing and it failed." And
typically, of course, I ask, "Okay, tell
me a little bit what happened." Yeah,
"Well, we had Kafka. Kafka was our event
store." And then this is the whole
story. I don't need to hear anything
else. Kafka is neither an event store
nor is it suitable for event sourcing.
It's a completely different thing. Of
course, it failed.
But that's not a problem of event
sourcing. That's just you try to do
something with a tool completely
unsuitable for it. Just to be clear for
our listeners that have never seen or
heard of Kafka, what is Kafka quickly?
Kafka is basically is an event streaming
platform. So that's the crucial
difference between event sourcing and
event streaming. If you want to think
about it, Kafka is basically it's like
the highway between your systems. So
what Kafka is perfect for and it was
very, very good at, it can transport
information from A to B in light speed,
super, super fast. That's what Kafka is
for. It's your highway between systems.
But if you want to know what happens
within your system, if you want to
record the decisions and the the history
of your information, that's what we talk
about event sourcing, but that's a
completely different story than the
highway. Can we say that Kafka is more
about to implement some kind of
communication protocol, not a storage of
events?
Basically, yes. So you put information
on the wire in one system and it comes
out in the other system and there in
between there's only 2 milliseconds
because Kafka is super, super fast.
But there it's not suitable for event
sourcing, absolutely not. So please,
please don't use Kafka as an event
store. Yeah, it's one of the things you
were saying before, maybe people get
confused between event sourcing and
event streaming, what they are.
All the time. All the time. I know that
you are teaching so I said Kafka was the
wrong technology. But in general, what
kind of systems is event sourcing more
suitable for? That's a very interesting
question and my opinion here is a little
bit contrary to what most people in the
industry are saying. Listen in the
industry what people are saying,
typically they say the default is CRUD
and only if you have a very specific use
case, you should use event sourcing. So
event sourcing is not for everything,
only use it if you have a very specific
use case. For example, you are working a
regulated industry, you have a lot of
audits that you need to make, stuff like
that, then you use event sourcing. My
opinion is a completely different one. I
say event sourcing is always the default
because it's a simpler way to build
system and only if there is a very, very
specific reason, I would fall back to
building a crap based system. So, the
only reason I would build a crap based
system is if I clearly have only a crap
based application which is basically
just a form with a lot of information
that I need to store. But even then, the
problem is those forms typically, sooner
or later, also turn into real
applications, into real business
processes and then you would also
benefit there from event sourcing. So,
if you ask me, I would always use event
sourcing and only in a very, very tiny
fraction of systems I would fall back to
crap. Okay, because I was also thinking,
you know, thinking with differently. So,
to me, tell me if I'm wrong, okay? So,
to me seems that it's mostly around
enterprise applications, you know, when
we model business processes. But for
example, developers that work in the
space of more embedded systems or things
like this, I guess they for those kind
of systems is not necessarily good idea
to think about that. Yes, that really
depends. So,
algorithmic systems, like if you use
operating systems, very low-level stuff,
embedded systems, they of course you
need to look is event sourcing the real
thing. So, where event sourcing really
shines is everything about information
management. So, Okay. the typical
systems you see in in the enterprise,
you put in information, this gets
transformed, you have many ways how this
information is used. If you need to
track how information is used along a
single timeline, that's typically where
event sourcing really shines. If you use
algorithms and stuff like that, of
course, that might not be the best use
case. Okay. Okay. In terms of trade-offs
that the team should consider. So,
between event source architecture and
let's say and call it a more traditional
one, yeah? But you say say instead of
event sourcing we use let's say a
relational database or well, maybe even
not the necessary relational, but
without storing events as we do with
event sourcing, yeah? So, are there any
trade-offs there in that we need to
consider for this choice? You know, I
don't know anything in terms of could be
performances, could be space on this,
could be anything. Yes, of course, there
are a few. So, the first thing you need
to consider when you think about
adopting event sourcing is it's a very
different mindset you need. So, you
cannot just tell your your developers,
"From today on, we will be doing event
sourcing and everything will be fine."
That is typically doomed to fail. That
will not work. So, the first thing you
need is you need the right mindset. And
uh this takes quite a while. It also
took me almost 2 years to get rid of all
those ideas I learned in the past and um
build systems the way I build systems
today using slices. It's a very
different thing. You cannot just tell
your developers to do it from now on and
it will work. Most probably, that is
doomed to fail. So, it takes a while to
get into this mindset. And the hardest
part with this is typically really
unlearning what you have learned. So,
building systems like this requires you
to unlearn quite a few things you might
think of as best practices today, which
in event sourcing are simply no longer
best practices. They are rather problems
you you try to prevent. But, of course,
also
other trade-offs might be you need to
build up the right infrastructure to do
event sourcing. And this doesn't have to
be an commercial product. So, you can
start very small, like with a Postgres
database using a relational database. I
have a lot of clients that simply use a
Postgres database as an event store. Or
some even use a Microsoft MS SQL Server
as an event store. That is perfectly
fine. So, typically, the the entry
barrier is very low. But, of course, to
do this right, also if it comes to
scale, if you build bigger systems, you
need to consider quite a few things
because even a Postgres database, which
is really, really powerful, if you have
enough events in your system, it becomes
slow. There's something you need to
consider. And then oftentimes, you need
to evaluate, does it make sense to have
a commercial product? And there are
quite a few commercial products
available to do that. Especially in the
beginning, that the entry barrier is
really, really low. And many systems
will never reach that scale. Most
systems are rather small, so most
systems don't reach that scale where
where your database will get into
trouble. But some systems do, and then
you need to consider what to do with it.
Okay. And now, going back to the
unlearning, what kind of
things developers need to unlearn that
that are maybe best practices with their
previous approach to software
development that are not really best
practices when using event sourcing?
Especially at the combination of event
sourcing and uh slice-based
architectures require a completely
different thinking. And the one thing I
struggled with the most was reuse, code
reuse.
It's basically it's non-existent in my
projects. I don't have any code reuse.
Because when you work with those slices,
you keep those slices independent.
They're very small, but they're
completely independent. And what you
can't do is there is no code reuse
between those slices. So, you cannot
just have any abstract classes. I I
didn't use any abstract classes in
5 years or so. I I never used that
because it creates a lot of coupling.
So, the whole DRY principles, don't
repeat yourself,
for most developers that means, oh, I I
have functionality implemented in one
part of the system, and I will just
reuse it from everywhere.
But this creates a lot of coupling. And
in a slice-based architecture, that
doesn't work because you want those
slices to be independent. So, what you
do is oftentimes is you copy
information. You copy code between those
slices. And it's perfectly fine to do
that. So, building slice-based systems
means a lot of copying. You copy-paste.
I'm extremely good at copy-pasting. And
nowadays, copy-paste means generating
with AI. That's That's just copy copy
and paste on steroids. It's the same
thing. Many developers really, really
struggle with this. Actually, now they
say, "Okay, we'll copy and paste." But
does this create issues like you have to
change some logic, and then you have to
change the same logic in all the places
where you did the copy and paste? Or the
copy and paste is actually in this
particular context is not affected by
these problems. Of course, that can
happen, but what typically happens is
since we model the system first with the
event modeling, typically this logic
isn't spread out throughout the whole
system. Typically, you have one slice
that takes care of this. Of course,
there can be something that is copied to
a few other slices, so can happen that
you need to adjust two or three
projections, for example, if you change
an event. That that's perfectly fine,
that can happen, but it's not that bad
as it sounds. So, typically, logic in
the system is very contained in slices.
That's what I'm seeing again and again.
And also, I really completely lost any
fear of copying also because of AI,
because AI can tell you very, very well,
"Okay, if you change this, those two or
three other places also need to be
adjusted." So, if you ask me that that
is really no longer a problem at all.
Mhm. Okay, so when rolling out this
event sourcing, so let's say my company
that has never done it before, yeah? So,
first of all,
well, we said the technical trade-offs,
but what about the business trade-offs?
So, why should a company consider, you
know, moving whatever systems they have
into a different design using event
event sourcing? What kind of advantages
they can get out of doing this?
Yes. The biggest advantage, and that was
also the reason why I initially went
into that direction, slice-based
architecture event sourcing, is whenever
you work on a traditional architecture,
in the beginning it's it's easy. It's no
problem. That's also same idea with the
greenfield project. When you start, it's
very easy because there are not a lot of
features. You can implement those
features in isolation typically, and
everything is fine. But the longer you
work in those systems, the more those
features have cross-dependencies, the
more they depend on each other. What
we're talking about, of course, is
coupling. The longer you work in those
projects, the more coupling accumulates.
If you don't invest heavily to get rid
of that. So, if you don't do constant
refactorings and uh keep the coupling
very contained, coupling just grows in
the system. And this means those systems
they get slower in terms of development
speed, and they get more expensive
because in the beginning you build one
feature and you're good, but later in
the project you build one feature, but
then you also need to adjust those five
other features because they all depend
on each other. That's what makes what
makes late-stage development very, very
expensive. So the longer you work on
those projects, the more expensive it
gets. And this is where
almost all companies just struggle.
That's a problem that haunts us for two
decades already and much longer. And
that I never found a solution to this.
So my my whole career I was struggling
with this. How can we do this the right
way? And it was really hard, always
hard, until I started to work with
slices. Because if you work with slices,
any new feature you throw at the system,
it doesn't matter which one. Any new
feature is typically just a new slice.
So your architectures, they have a flat
cost curve. The cost curve is very flat.
You don't have this hockey stick
exponential growing cost curve. It's
very flat. No matter what requirements
you add to the system, you just add new
slices. It's almost like an append-only
architecture. Just adding new slices,
which means since those slices are
independent from each other, you don't
touch them. They almost behave like
small, tiny little microservices within
your system. You only touch those slices
if the requirements change, and that is
such a beautiful way of working because
you never have to look at uh the whole
code base. You never have to look at,
"Okay, what did I break now by this
change?" Because change is only for one
slice and one slice only. This is really
it's a great way to develop systems
because your time to market with this is
just amazing. And what's also amazing is
if you work with AI, and I mean every
company nowadays tries to find good ways
to work with AI, your coding agent never
has to understand the whole code base.
It just has to understand one slice. And
this might be just five classes, for
example. So you never need this uh 1
million token context window because
typically the tasks you use for your
coding agents, they are very, very
small. So it's a very good way to to
integrate AI into the development
process. Okay, and since you mentioned
before that it is actually difficult to
get started with it for developers and
have to change the mindset and
everything. So,
then
a company that decides to go in that
direction, how would you recommend them
them to get started? You know, training
developers or hire the right people?
What is that your suggestion for a
company that decides to go into this
direction? The first step is always even
modeling. So, I wouldn't start with
event sourcing. The precondition for
event sourcing is some way of
collaborative modeling and my choice is
always even modeling because it for me
it's the simplest way, but also event
storming, all those methodologies help.
There's also domain storytelling. They
are all wonderful all wonderful
methodologies. Just my my choice is even
modeling because it it it fits so well.
So, the first thing I would always
recommend is start by modeling, start by
understanding your business processes.
Don't think about technology. Start by
understanding your business process. You
can even do this for your current
database systems. You don't have to do
event sourcing to start with modeling.
You get the all the benefits of even
modeling today with your existing
system. That that's perfectly fine.
But then if you started to model those
systems and you really understand those
processes, there's a natural way to
transition from an event model to an
event source system. So, if you do did
the modeling correct and you you trained
your people on doing this, this can be
by workshops, this can be just by
bringing in people who help. There are
many ways to do this or just give them
my book to read. That's also a good
starting point. So, there are many ways
to to get started. And even modeling is
really it's a simple methodology. You
getting started is really really simple.
But when they master that, that's
already the first step to change this
mindset. The mindset changes. People
start to think about processes. They
don't no longer think about databases
and tables and microservices. They start
to think about processes and this
changes a lot. And what you typically do
then is if you have to see the model,
you just have to look at the event model
and you see what would be a good
candidate. Can Is there something we can
extract from our legacy system? Is there
Oh, there's a small process here. How
about we make this a new microservice?
And we just make a proof of concept. You
typically start with a proof of concept.
You don't do a big bang and then say,
"From today on, everything is event
sourcing." That's typically not what
happens. You start with a small proof of
concept. One tiny little process. Let's
build a microservice using event
sourcing. Let's build a blueprint
architecture. How would a blueprint
architecture for us look like? What's
the stack we are using? There are many
different stacks. If it's .NET, you
might use Martin and Wolverine. If it's
on the JVM, typically might be Axon.
There are many different ways how to get
started. Or many companies start to
build their own frameworks, which is
also fine. So,
very easy to get started typically. Of
course, when it comes to scale, you
might want to use an established
framework, but
just for our first proof of concept,
it's perfectly fine to build your own
event sourcing framework, and it's fun.
Let's Let's face it, it's fun to build
your own framework, so why not invest a
little bit of time with AI? This can be
done in 1 or 2 days, so it's it's really
not a big thing anymore. And then if you
have this first proof of concept that is
running, maybe even in production, what
you will realize is you achieved a lot
in a very short period of time. So, it's
it's crazy how fast you can build those
systems if you combine event modeling,
event sourcing, and the slice-based
architecture. Within 2 days, you can
have a system running in production.
It's crazy how fast you can go with
this. And typically, those systems,
since they are built together by
business and engineering in
collaboration, they are exactly what
those people need. So, typically, they
are very successful in production. You
mentioned legacy system. So, with a
legacy system, then I guess that you
would start with maybe you said start
with event modeling. So, I would imagine
part of that would be modeling what the
system currently does, at least for the
Yes. Parts that are interesting. And
then what would you do? Then you choose
where to start as in you said creating a
prototype or some microservices or
something else to start to change the
legacy system into the new shape. Yes,
that's typically what happens. So, in
the last months I support many clients
in modernizing legacy systems and what
I'm basically doing is I'm using AI to
analyze existing systems and build event
models from this basically
automatically. And this works really
well and I'm I'm doing this from two
sides typically. So, I use AI agents to
analyze the existing code base and I use
AI agents to go through the UI. So, if
if there is a UI, you can just use them
to go through the UI and basically build
the event models from the UI just to
understand the processes. And you can
also automatically take those
screenshots, put them into the event
model. It's quite interesting. What
you're basically doing is you gather a
lot of information about the system
because what most companies struggle
with is they have those big gigantic
systems that make a lot of money
typically, but they don't really know
how they work because the this knowledge
is retired or it's gone to other
companies, it's no longer there. So,
they have a lot of information in those
systems, but they don't know how that
works. And if you ask me, before you do
any modernization, any code, before you
write the first line of code for any
modernization, the first thing you need
to do is completely understand how does
the system work. You cannot modernize
what you don't understand. That is
doomed to fail. So, you really need to
understand how that works. And using
event modeling for that is is a very
good step because you bring all those
people together and you can extract the
knowledge that is available, use AI to
fill in the gaps. That works really
really well. And instead for a
greenfield system, can you have an
approach that is kind of incremental?
So, what I mean is maybe you have some
event modeling workshop, but then you
are not quite sure about the entire
system or the direction and but you know
some initial parts. So, can you actually
do this thing in a incremental iterative
manner?
Yes. Yes, absolutely. So, what we
typically do is we start to model, but
we don't model the whole system and then
we start. What we typically do is we
model the system on a very high level,
then we pick one tiny workflow that we
are pretty sure about, that we
understand. Okay, let's take the
registration. We know how the our works.
Let's start with that. And maybe it's
just five slices.
Five slices is enough to get started.
Write some code, build a proof of
concept, bring it to pre-production or
even to production, it doesn't really
matter. This piece of the software is
already done. And then we can decide,
okay, based on the event model, uh what
is the next process we want to tackle?
Where do we have the most knowledge now?
Where are the least gaps? And then we
might do that. So, you can build it
very, very incrementally, step by step.
Even if you want slice by slice, that's
also possible. So, yes, that that's
typically the way to go. And this also
gives you the possibility to change
directions. So, you don't have to have
those long project plans and the plan
the whole migration.
You can go very small, step by step. And
if you if you find out, well, this goes
in a very wrong direction, you can
always change directions, because it's
slice by slice. You can basically change
on a daily basis, if you want. And in
terms of testability, in terms of, you
know, testing, unit testing, various
levels of testing, are there any
differences between event sourcing
systems and more traditional ones?
So, what I'm using heavily, really,
really heavily, is behavior-driven
development, and that's a very good
combination together with event sourcing
systems. So, basically, we do this on a
slice by slice basis, and you do this
also already in event modeling. You
define basically, what are the
acceptance criteria? What are the
business rules for one slice, using
given-when-then? It's just Let's make an
example, and maybe that's the the
easiest thing. Let's say we have this
customer registration, and there's just
a rule, we only allow customers with the
same uh surname once in the system. You
would have a given event, given there is
already a customer with the surname,
when I try to register this customer
again, or another customer with the same
surname, then this might would be an
exception, for example. So, you describe
all those business rules for each slice
in the system.
What I do is I use the given-when-then
specifications from the event model, and
I generate executable specifications in
code. And this is such a great way of
working, because those specifications in
the event model are defined by the
business people. So, this is the real
business rules. You're not talking about
technical unit tested test things that
are not important. We are testing the
real business rules that are defined by
the business people. And if you
translate them to executable
specifications and all those
specifications are green, there's a very
high chance that the system does exactly
what it needs to do.
Okay. And now a final question actually.
So, have you got any suggestion for
metrics or signals or anything that can
be used to demonstrate that, you know,
using an event modeling well, an event
sourcing system is actually improving
delivery? Because you see, a company
that invests on it say, "Okay, we want
to invest on this thing. We have a
system, an existing one, we want to go
into this direction instead which seems
to be better, but what kind of metrics
they should look at to decide that
actually changing into an event sourcing
system they have a good return on
investment?"
Yeah, so what I use as a measurement is
really I call it the slice cycle time.
So, the slice cycle time is basically
how long does it take a team to build
one slice? So, what we typically do is
we start with a with an event modeling
workshop that lasts typically for 3
days. We do 2 days of event modeling,
modeling a process, and the third day is
typically building the system. What we
start to do there is we define the
blueprint architecture. What does a
slice look like for the company? And
then what you start to measure is the
slice cycle time. How long does it take
your team to build a slice? In the
beginning this will typically be around
two or three days maybe with AI that's
much shorter, but what you measure is
how long does it does it take my team to
build a slice? And if you do this long
enough, what you will realize is this
cycle time will get smaller and smaller.
So, in the end it might just be half a
day for example to build a full slice.
And this includes the UI. That's a whole
piece of functionality. And what you
then do is those slices they are
production ready if you do it right. So,
you can build those small pieces of
functionality and you can continuously
deliver those slices to production. That
means your time to production will be
extremely short. So, you you can deliver
multiple times a day
working software to production. Of
course, that also works with other
methodologies. Event sourcing is not the
only thing, but a team that starts to
work like this typically increases the
deliveries to production massively. And
that's that's typically what I try
companies to really adopt and where they
should go to. Okay. Thank you. I think
we have come to the end of the episode.
Yeah, yeah. And I think we give an quite
a good introduction to the audience.
I hope so.
Yeah. Is there anything you'd like to
add, Martin? I would really encourage
companies, teams,
give it a try. It's not a big
investment. It could be what we did with
many clients was just it's called a
FedEx day. FedEx day is just that you
take one day
and at the end of the day you need to
deliver like FedEx. This could be a
perfect starting point. Take one day and
make sure that to deliver something at
the end of the day. And I guarantee you
you will be positively surprised what is
possible to do within a day if you bring
the people together. Okay. Thank you
very much, Martin. Thank you for coming
to the show and it's been a real
pleasure. And this is Johannes
Schbringer for Software Engineering
Radio. Thank you for listening.
[music]
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more [music]
about the podcast, including other
episodes, visit our website at
SE-Radio.net.
[music]
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
[music] through our Slack channel at
SE-Radio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
[music]
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
License 2.5.
Thanks for listening.